japan's a nation there is influence the
world
so many ways be it through their
technology
for their contributions the popular
culture like video games
the many diverse the music and video
games read more in our house
growing up then any other form music at
the time
yet for most diverse the composer's
behind these timeless melodies remain
face digging in the cards is about
unearthing the men and women who
inspired
an entire generation arguably creating
Japan's biggest musical
export to the world
up
had season-ending accusing and I no no I
didn't mean on that one
doing so to the community yet top cool
factor that's why you many more why I
don
martini I don't like to go out think
I'ma ma'am on all this time you know
im so sorry we're going up the
here
the higher numbers and she's la
now mine authority on that CD min on
as you think I the announcement Donovan
unionists slogan
drama
glass Curtice happiness day Mustang
non-smoking
cumed in your music only did your
mountains did
conceived small think not music addict
in a game or not gonna conscripted
about in the month now with our do about
this
what a crazy crazy franchise wouldn't
beautiful RPG world that they created
not quite the final one
yeah the you know it did
its the most fun I've had playing video
games was playing file
said and music though music closest
Nobuo Uematsu
is the game music guy
Final Fantasy 7 that soundtrack is like
the quintessential
music is great in games so I think it's
getting late you know this is hard
begins can be beautiful
well
limited although this it on the game on
a almost up to blow up to us
mall rules in one hr tossed into the one
at the pool on
home all numbing a whole sculptors minor
chords can people do what mister
your mobile caudal seasonal to see the
listener dies this
%uh %uh
do
lose you old she will sign a little too
stunned
all the possible so hot political not
gonna pass on the calypso more
digital will take a morning in this
article was a little longer
what I will deliver a comical up there
bullying the
lost my hearing on the school my bones
love for you will appeal to the last
month the
sure I got on that day to the sort I
short discussion that day
shuttle kind that it died soil cell it's
not that skilled norm
saludable here to my vocal overtones
that
this work on your machine what a game or
two doubled up to
little well sole member claudine the
to call given in Chi tonight do what it
did
this fall on its authority to Los quayle
bosnia
the
plan a month urging resubmit on other it
included a pickup in on the scandal
wat else could to put on it symbol look
closely with a low
Polak the got a little walk to the pool
both local so he end up there to Queen
como opening them in the identical to
the grid the top 100 was kinda
do it there the haha tip
Scott tunnel would they lost their
school a couple months
hi animal diseases puts coral on UN will
wanna
both duh
do
deal little cousin all honey along the
Indus to the super high school
old in with the QR above the screen of
death all the horses absolutely and got
a little delayed a little
probably going to food times the
headline disorder
need internet to haul Siggins how it was
handled all
not books you'll the school has minimal
their
blossoms home did blow up doll book book
about the beautiful girl
not to cross boiler political party all
japanese couple shingles so dazzling
title game
do not understand
versatile tool
all just a little Universal's cable
thought on to star shovel so that ousted
in water
all lazy middle deal that %uh solicitor
devils food lol
she also talked with rusted
or political timing what sauce in the
city so suitable
total days you'll not only did
non-alcohol
dominici you don't know what it is on
the shores of the panel
will not understand so little for
promotional crucible force Toledo
you look on this deal the most other
bowl curse upon colonial
caught up with them up small stop the
law someone in all
daschle's whole gonna something rules
till now
to the hospital some political surviving
mobile to pc
it to be asleep the BBQ
no on the schedule I mean cool looking
all that muscle little table
love the style super horrible well
competent enough that I know
should I up there with this
hope coolidge rule applies a little the
study is also the tunnel
law couple heineman dozen reach Tony the
lot darker more
squeal is Cup all cattle plot does
local local local local water when you
get an Icee one in Flint are you only
got another couple little
not in England malls hindsight
I also know cook-outs I'll Bowl
according to still
shot june englishman click Upload the
locals alike
I'm
are nearer time music director and
conductor distant worlds music from
Final Fantasy
Justin wells is dedicated to presenting
music a Final Fantasy
as close to the way as it was originally
heard in the game
as possible
on little somethings the law
distant laudable conduct old steel the
above the focal orchestra across a good
ties to the pulpit
sewed up there slowly Musina proceeds to
handle
to channels that both the same wise to
be the film also personal
today gonna pop the tunnels the skin on
death
hear their product that many of the same
musical influences
so we constantly are talking back and
forth about these things
I'll never forget the first year I was
doing something dear friends cancers and
came out to one of them
be riding in the car to an after
rehearsal and
said you know number son is very funny
every time
I'm working on online angel with an
orchestra
I hear Jimi Hendrix Purple Haze
his that's what I was thinking up when I
wrote this
overwhelmingly the concert feels
like a a beautiful family gathering
up everyone single-mindedly loves Final
Fantasy music and wants to be there for
that reason
so it's very embracing up there was some
sitting in the audience with us
there's a lot of electricity right from
the beginning
there are some themes
that go back to choke about themore
Eunos some these very early themes
that are still in use today maybe 50 or
100 variations later
but we see the same fanatical response
to those themes
some things that he attempted were
outrageously difficult that them to deal
with this computer chip Olympic
character
how to inject emotion and fear
drama you know into it and he was able
to do with music and that can translate
that wanted full orchestration
is also a testament to the way he wrote
know the instructor first
hi looking for a needle just don't want
a beloved
shovel local players also texted yaaaay
not Wilton
numb down the 100 on a possible the
Ramadi
humble pie tonight by slot that got our
I
uni but no you ni nonlethal call school
my name is Sir Thomas poker hand the
producer of
video game music concerts scenes eleven
years now
day I D behind China symphony is
for sending the musical Final Fantasy in
a very
that's a classical way what we are doing
is
retelling the story is of the games
western music
2003 it was the first
b2b music concert from outside of Japan
and was my very first concert which are
produced and
we got where noble month so to
attend this concert so this was his
first time that he went
outside of Japan to attend a concert
with his music performed by an orchestra
he was I think quite amazed to see that
in the European orchestra was performing
his music and
there are many fans also asking for
autographs lol
final hunters squarely del myer
module did susceptible see what all
hostility little their solution to put
the law
%um a lot listener
I'm
final symphony companies to 3
pieces basically there's the symphonic
poem a poem based on
Final Fantasy X and then the piano
concert though
based on teams from Final Fantasy 10 and
finally
than this magnificent symphony based on
the music from Final Fantasy seven
one of the greatest things with this
concert just justice them
before the audience they really have
this verse from emotional
connection to the music and I know with
myself also I'm
complains games as a kid and not only
does it bring back memories of the games
but like
from the whole a row my life
I hear quite often from Japanese
composers that day never clicked
expected there so famous and well-known
outside of Japan
they are telling me that there were just
sitting in their small rooms
working under very tight deadline
to finish his work and they and they
always start like maybe a few people
would listen to it
and then out of a sudden they are like
sitting in a concert hall there's two
thousand people a cheering when
only his name is mentioned it
the No
on the final composition religious link
on did
also look at the council additional
the civil born tunnels and a scope to
cause luck with that
a little under she went to movie
channels open come called
all should see to modernize unable to
any
so you only taking them will not leave
us there