(Narrator) Japan is a nation that has
influenced the world in so many ways.
Be it there food,
their technology,
or their contributions to popular culture
like video games.
For many of us
the music of video games played more
in our households growing up
than any other form of music at the time.
Yet for most of us, the composers behind
these timeless melodies remain faceless.
DIGGIN' IN THE CARTS is about
unearthing the men & women
who inspired an entire generation
while arguably creating Japan's biggest
musical export to the world.
Ten, nine, eight, seven, six,
five, four, three, two, one
(beep)
(laughter)
- Captured?
- Captured!
(Narrator) As the 80's drew to a close
the video game industry was booming.
16-bit technology had arrived
and changed the face of gaming forever
as various consoles competed to bring
the next generation arcade experience
to homes around the world.
♪(DRAGON SPIRIT)♪
When the 16-bit era arrived,
everyone thought it was a revolution.
The graphics became very beautiful,
and the music very grand.
♪(DRAGON SPIRIT continues)♪
The PC Engine (TurboGrafx-16)
came out first,
It has been referred to as 16-bit,
but strictly speaking
it was half 8-bit and half 16-bit.
The Mega Drive (Genesis) which came after
It was a complete16-bit console.
It was exciting to think that we could play
the same games as at the arcades.
♪(The Revenge of Shinobi)♪
(Man) 8-bit go to 16-bit,
it was such a leap
It was my favourite era of
video gaming, I think.
16-bit arrival was when you were like
Wow! The Background moves!
(LadyHawke) I couldn’t even comprehend
game graphics getting any better.
(laughs)
The music improved and
the graphics improved, and with that
it became possible to express things
that had previously been impossible
With that, I think game music evolved
into something
very cinematic and dramatic.
♪(LARGE GREEN MEADOW continues)♪
(Man) I'm Hayato Matsuo.
I think I started the work about 25 years ago.
♪(LARGE GREEN MEADOW continues)♪
(Matsuo) As you've heard,
I feel this is a dark track
that has power.
Listening to this,
I particularly remember that
how to handle the bass
was often a problem.
We tried a lot of things,
and after trial and error,
in the end, listening to it now,
I think we may have even put in
too much bass.
♪("Golden Warrior"
from Master of Monsters)♪
(Matsuo) At first, it started with the NES,
which had 3 sounds
and then moved to 16-bit,
where memory suddenly increased,
which was a big change.
When it became 7 or 8 sounds
the world really opened up
and there weren't just PSG sounds,
but also FM sounds too.
Expansions in the tones
and the number of ports was inspiring.
♪("Golden Warrior" continues)♪
There was someone I worked with
often back then,
a man named Hitoshi Sakimoto.
I think he is someone who will always
have a place in the history of game music.
♪(WALTZ OF MEDITATION PART 2 continues)♪
(Man) Waltz of Meditation Part 2,
despite it being a shooting game,
the heroine was a cute girl
I wanted to accurately portray
the feelings of the cute girl
making her way through a harsh world
while fighting hard.
Beautiful yet scary,
scary, yet beautiful.
♪(WALTZ OF MEDITATION PART 2 continues)♪
(Man) I'm Hitoshi Sakimoto.
My job is composing music
and running a sound production company.
I've been doing this job for 25 years.
♪(RIPPLE'S THEME from Magical Chase)♪
The first time I took an interest
in the sound of games was probably…
with sound effects rather than music itself.
The early ones that come to mind are
Space Invaders and Galaxian.
There was a game called
The Tower of Druaga back then,
and the music was fantastic.
(Sakimoto) I recorded it at the arcade
with what you'd call a Walkman nowadays.
I cranked up the volume pretty high
when I listened to it.
For people of my parents' generation,
it was like a cacophony
they said something like,
"Have you gone mad?"
♪(WALTZ OF MEDITATION PART 1
from Magical Chase)♪
(Sakimoto) I'm often asked about
the limitations of old sound chips.
We have been challenging the limitations.
When it came to playing drums
with such old sound chips...
Even now, real drum sounds are
hard to reproduced.
(Sakimoto) As for real drum kit or percussion kit,
I gave up imitating them at a very early stage.
But we tried our best
not to care so much about it.
Taking on the challenge of facing
those limitations was really fun for us.
♪("SHINMACHI"
from The Adventures Of Hourai High)♪
♪(SHINMACHI continues)♪
Everyone loves the sound of old games, and
they often tell me how wonderful it was.
I'm really happy about that itself, but
I definitely don't feel like going back then.
You needed to devote so much time to things
that were not actual music.
(Sakimoto) and it was such a tough situation
to be in. (laughs)
I do think it'll be fun to get together
with developers from back then
and share war stories over a drink.
I never want to go back.
(laughs)
♪ (CAPCOM's sound logo) ♪
♪ (SIBERIAN TUNNEL from Strider)♪
(Uchizawa) Back then Capcom was
a company that made good action games.
♪(OPENING THEME from Street Fighter 2)♪
Oh! Street Fighter!
Oh!!
♪(GUILE'S THEME from Street Fighter 2)♪
- (Ryu) Tatsumaki Senpu-Kyaku!
- (Guile) Sonic boom!
(Man) First time I actually saw
Street Fighter 2
I used to see the older boys playing it
like banging it out,
that was the thing to do
After school, before school,
lunchbreak whatever.
People were just in there rinsing out.
Street Fighter 2 was so big in my area.
There was one in a newsagent,
(Ikonoka) one in a video shop,
one in a Doner Kebab shop.
They were just everywhere.
So many quarters…. So many quarters…
And you would always try and steal 30p.
Oh mum give me, what change have you got?
Like that kind of things, run over
to the shop, have one play, lose.
(laughs)
Go back home, ask for more money.
♪(KEN'S THEME from Street Fighter 2)♪
- (Ken) Hadoken!
- (Zangief screaming)
The music on SF2 was a big enough
influence to make me want to sample it.
In my archive, for people
that have been into me since early
That’s one of their favourite songs.
Before I made it onto the TV,
before anything like that,
when I was just making instrumentals.
Streetfighter was a big influence.
And all the sound effects as well.
Thundercat, when you text him
it’s like “Sho-Ryu Ken”.
SF2 – That game's music was like,
it made you feel like a champion,
even if you suck.
(Ken) Tatsumaki Senpu-Kyaku!
(Narrator) You lose!
Even at the end when you die
it’s like the greatest,
grandest death ever.
You died but you tried
as hard as you could.
How do you make music
that sounds like that you know?
♪(GAME OVER from Street Fighter 2)♪
(screaming)
SF2 was a hit around the world,
as well as in Japan.
It became a household name.
It was originally an arcade game,
but was also ported to the SNES.
People were excited about playing
the arcade game at home,
so everyone bought it and played it.
♪(CHUN-LI'S THEME continues)♪
(Woman) I'm Yoko Shimomura.
I'm from Osaka, now I live in Tokyo.
I've been composing game music
for 26 years.
When it was decided that I'd be doing SF2,
in general the planner explained
what kind of songs they wanted.
He gave me a kind of list.
There were different scenes.
I suggested the idea of,
rather than character theme songs
how about making background music
with the feeling of each country instead.
♪(DHALSIM'S THEME from Street Fighter 2 )
When I suggested that making
some kind of world music
with a comical taste might be funny.
They said it was fine,
and we went with it.
♪(DHALSIM'S THEME continues)♪
(Man) I love how everyone has their theme,
they’re all from a different place in the world.
So they kind of like themed after the location
and the sound of the music where they’re from.
My favourite one of course was Ryu’s,
you know?
That’s ‘cause it was like “Fight to live &
live to fight”. That's what it felt like.
♪(RYU'S THEME from Street Fighter 2)♪
Guile's theme gets you pumped up,
Ken’s theme is like rock ‘n’ roll
‘cause he’s a dude from California.
(Man) You go to China you got
the whole Chinese theme.
You go to USA and
it’s like the American theme…
(humming)
It's just fit.
My favourite probably was Blanka’s theme.
♪(Humming and tapping knees
to keep rhythm)♪
♪(BLANKA'S THEME from Street Fighter 2)♪
The Blanka theme was tight.
The way it would speed up
and the progression of that.
And by the end of the round
it’s all fast stuff,
and it’s all tense,
and you’re in the Jungle.
I'm really surprised that there are
so many people who like the Blanka theme.
For Blanka's song,
the rhythm like "tan ta ta",
the "taka tan tan" kind of rhythm
came to me really quickly.
The rhythm was basically done,
but I couldn't come up with a melody
even late in development.
So one morning on a commuter train
I was thinking,
if I didn't finish Blanka's song
I wouldn't make the deadline.
I was thinking about Blanka on a train.
I was standing near the door,
and there was the rack on the top,
there was a greenish yellow paper bag
on top of that.
As soon as I saw it,
I thought about Blanka's colour
the melody just came
into my head like that.
"Tararirarin" was in my head and I thought,
"This is it!"
After that I was humming
"tararirarin, tararirarin"
humming it the whole time
while walking to work,
and I said Good Mornin',
then went straight to my seat
to write down the tararirarin,
That's the Blanka's theme.
I can only thank
the paper bag on the train.
♪(BLANKA'S THEME continues)♪
♪(Humming BLANKA'S THEME
and tapping knees to keep rhythm)♪
and then it's like...
(humming BLANKA'S THEME)
Oh man.
♪(BLANKA'S THEME continues)♪
♪(VEGA'S THEME from Street Fighter 2)♪
(Shimomura) I made all the sound effects for SF2
and recorded the voices too.
I remember feeling really impressed
when I took a trip to Spain.
There was a Spanish bar,
the kids from the neighbourhood
would come in from outside
and go straight to the SF2 machine
and start playing.
And the Spaniard kids were saying,
'dosukoi' (a sumo exclamation).
At that time I thought it was amazing
and I felt kind of proud.
- (Narrator) You Win!
- (E. Honda) Dosukoi!
♪(E. HONDA'S THEME from SF2)
(Ken) Hadoken! Shoryuken!
I'm happy that so many kids from overseas
learned that Japanese from the game.
I didn't think that would happen at all.
Thanks to SF2,
I gained a lot of confidence.
It allowed me to leave
an impression on others.
It's really all thanks to SF2.
♪(AIRPLANE
from The Adventures Of Hourai High)♪