Japan is a nation that has influenced
the world in so many ways
Be it there food,
their technology,
or their contributions to popular culture
like Video Games
For many of us
the music of video games played more
in our households growing up
than any other form of music at the time
Yet for most of us,
the composers behind these timeless melodies
remain faceless
DIGGIN' IN THE CARTS is
about unearthing the men & women
who inspired an entire generation
while arguable creating Japan's biggest
musical export to the world.
♪(beep)♪
By the end of the 1980's, Japan entered the economic bubble
and stock and real estate prices soared to new heights
Video Games were becoming more beautiful and complex
and composers from companies
like Konami and Sunsoft
pushed technology to its limits
and improved the quality of video game music
♪("Gradius")♪
Konami was developing and releasing
a lot of really innovative games back then
it's a game company that produced a lot of big hits
Konami originally had been working hard
in releasing titles for the arcades
before they broke out into the NES
They were already heavily involved in creating sound
and they were predicted to be the next big thing after Namco
No one gives Konami enough credit for
what they’ve done for music
Even still today
Konami games are very action orientated.
So they gave them music
that complimented the action
Very fast paced,
electric guitars & stuff like that.
That’s definitely rock-orientated
♪("Bloody Tears"
from Castlevania II: Simon's Quest)♪
Castlevania's music was groundbreaking
it also had a very dark feeling
and melodies that got into your head
The influence Castlevania had is immeasurable
It combined rock and baroque
and introduced the 'baroque-rock' genre
into video games
Baroque contains ultimate despair & ultimate joy
in one note
And somehow that was contained
in the music of ‘Castlevania’
It’s just some of the most beautiful
video game music ever made
♪("Contra")♪
Back in the day
Konami was putting stuff out like ‘Contra’
That had DPCM drum samples
that cut so hard
Obviously the most notorious cheat code
of all time comes from Contra
The music was pretty arpeggiated,
a lot of beats and stuff like that
Really rhythmic…..
♪(singing a tune)♪
Real syncopated patterns and shit
Contra? I mean come on. The illest
Too ill. Action you know what I’m saying – gets you hyped up
Super Mario was laid back with basslines
and kinda like a tropic type thing
And then you go to Contra,
you’re in the Jungle. It’s like real fast
♪("MASSACRE MOUNTAIN" continues)♪
A lot of people say
the music in Contra is
their favorite Konami music
Konami was most well known
for their technical prowess
They would apply all these really unusual
almost magical tricks and surprised us
Konami, they always put sound first
They were one of the few companies
that were developing for the NES
that decided they wanted to have
an extra sound chip
devoted to giving you three extra oscillators
So instead of just the two lead sounds,
they gave you four Square sounds,
and a Saw for bass!
People were shocked to hear
such thick sounds coming from the NES
By achieving this, the first game impressed players was
Castlevania III
♪("EPITAPH" continues)♪
Inserting a sound chip
into a NES game cartridge
you could play the cartridge sound
and the console sound in a hybrid manner
Konami had adopted this method
at quite an early stage
and the sound chip they inserted
into their cartridge was called
the VRC6
Even though when I was a kid I knew
that Konami had the best soundtracks
because it was apparent every single game
that they had made
sounded better than the competition
During 8-bit era, the NES game with the best sound quality
was Lagrange Point
Nobody else had thought of
inserting an FM synth into the cartridge
so it came as a big surprise
And when you actually played it,
the clear FM synth sound
would play from the 8-bit NES
it was bizarre and amazing and fantastic
♪("THEME OF ISIS" continues)♪
They created music with a strong emphasis
on the atmosphere and plot drama
so in my mind it's a very notable game
♪("Lagrange Point")♪
They didn't just use their staff sound composers
but also worked with J-Pop artists
like Akio Dobashi from Rebecca
♪("Lagrange Point" melody continues)♪
My name is Akio Dobashi
I'm a musician
I used to be in a band called Rebecca
After that, I wrote music for a Konami game
called Lagrange Point
Rebecca debuted in 1984
We reached No 1 in the Japanese chart
with our fourth album, Rebecca IV
Back then, rock bands rarely got to
number one
so selling a million records meant
we got a lot of publicity at the time
I was asked by Konami to compose game music
I think they wanted to start
adding deeper melodies
written by famous people into their games
And it ended up with me saying I'd give it a try
What Konami first asked me about was
the ending theme
the music that you hear
when you complete the game
I remember trying to mix
a sense of achivement
with a sense of security
when I create the melody
When my track was played at the end
I felt satisfied that I'd done a good job
(city noise)
It's been 30 years
since the golden days of the NES
but there are many people
who still want to hear
NES game music today
Hardcore fans of NES music were
also enjoying
listening to music from smaller
minor gaming companies
There are currently several record labels
around Japan
working hard to create such products
♪("Gremlins 2")♪
(Yoshikawa) I am Nobuhiro Yoshikawa
I make and produce soundtracks
for retro games
in Akihabara in Tokyo
Back in the days of the NES
all of the game makers showed
their unique colours
Sunsoft had something different from the other companies
Their use of sound was clearly different
from the other companies
The composers' original influences were
things like
classical, fusion and British ska
♪("Gremlins 2")♪
Sunsoft's games sales wasn't really big
compared to the big companies back then
So I guess, you can say
that a lot of masterpieces ended up buried
Of all the Sunsoft soundtracks
my favorite has to be Gimmick!
composed by Masashi Kageyama
♪("SOPHIA" continues)♪
My name is Masashi Kageyama
I used to write game music about 25 years ago
♪("SOPHIA" continues)♪
The music I was writing back then
I tried to make them as beautiful as possible
It was music children would listen to
so I wanted to make it fun and beautiful
so this towns in Shizuoka
and the nature like this
influenced me a lot
♪("JUST FRIENDS" continues)♪
In junior high and elementary school
I rode my bike
While I was riding my bike, I felt the cool breeze
♪("JUST FRIENDS" continues)♪
Back then I heard George Benson on the radio
it's the crossover music
I listened to a lot music and that kind of music
would play in my head
Ten minutes on my bike would mean
ten minutes ad libbing a melody
That's how it was
I think the games Sunsoft was putting out were
more crazy and unusual than the other companies
We were really able to compose
as we liked without any restrictions
♪("Gimmick!")♪
I think a big part of childrens experience
with music comes from games
When you reach a tricky stage,
you hear the music many times
since game music is looped
If the music is abrasive,
the game itself becomes tedious
so I wanted to make varied
high quality music for them to enjoy
♪("Gimmick!")♪
Back then, composing was a suprisingly tough job
When a new title came up
I doubted if I could do it
It was always in my mind
that I'd written this kind of song before
so now I had to go one better.
Those doubts started to consume me
Back then, I had no idea of
what people thought about my music
no feedback from
the people who listened were given
Maybe that's one of the reasons I ended up quitting
♪("Gimmick!")♪
Maybe four or five years ago on YouTube
I saw a group living in New York
who perform Bit Music live
and they'd played a few songs from my Gimmick!
They all knew the Gimmick! Music
and said it influenced them a lot
It made me really happy to hear that
Even though I quit music about 20 years ago
it made me feel like getting back into it
Receiving this kind of praise
makes me really happy
and I think it even encouraged me
to get back into music
I'm really grateful
♪("Hebereke")♪